Rhiannon: Mental health concerns
within the family may involve a
parent, a child, or a sibling or even
a grandparent, but whoever is affected,
the general effects of mental health
concerns, can have an impact on the
whole family and their relationships.
Knowledge that a parent is mentally ill
can be very difficult for a child or
young person as they may feel they are
to blame for any related behaviours.
Leah: Having a loved one, act violently
towards someone in the family will always
have a negative effect on mental health.
Children who witness or are subject
to violence at home, are likely to
suffer from depression or develop
more severe mental health issues.
Children may also have other concerns;
they may feel they are missing out,
because they’re looking after a family
member and doing jobs around the
house most people their age don’t do.
Some children feel ashamed about
their family member and do not
want to bring friends home, some
are even worried that they will
suffer from the same mental illness.
Rhiannon: As mental illness can
often appear in someone’s teens, it
is common for someone to be living
in the family home when their issues
become apparent, most commonly
anxiety disorders and depression.
However, in severe cases, children or
young people may express suicidal thoughts
or attempt suicide or may use drugs or
alcohol to cope with their feelings.
In these instances, a child’s mental
health concerns will most likely
require professional help and support.
Leah: The school environment has a
significant impact on a young person’s
emotional welfare and mental well-being.
An estimated three children in every
classroom suffer from a diagnosable
mental health problem and there is a
general trend to increased levels of
stress and lower levels of wellbeing.
Students with a poor standard of education
are more likely to experience mental
health problems, this has been attributed
to the fact that children from poorer
backgrounds, often do not have access
to the best standards of teaching.
Rhiannon: Some young people suffer
a lot of distress going to school
it could be due to relationships
with their peers, body image,
classroom anxiety or exam stress.
and the growing number of children
and young people experiencing
poor mental health is one of the
biggest challenges in the classroom.
Leah: Mental health problems in children
and young people cause distress and can
have wide-ranging effects, including
impacts on educational attainment
and family life and relationships,
as well as affecting physical health
and in severe cases, life chances.